António Miguel de Jesus Domingues

Schubertstrasse 31, 01307 Dresden, Germany

🛘 (+49) 01575-1976556 | 🔀 amjdomingues@gmail.com | 🏕 http://adomingues.github.io/ | 🖸 adomingues | 🛅 antonio-domingues

Summary_

Bioinformatician with more than 10 years experience in the analysis and integration of multi-omics datasets. Together with my background in experimental biology this gives me a unique perspective when communicating data analysis and results to stakeholders. I enjoy experimenting with data visualization to communicate results effectively, and to automate data process to deliver insights more efficiently.

Skills_

Core competencies Genomic data analysis, RNA-seq, small RNA-seq, ATAC-seq, Exosome sequencing, NGS

R/Bioconductor, bash, Python, bpipe (workflow manager), git, Cluster computing (LSF / SLURM), Markdown, LaTeX, statistics, **Programming**

AWS, Machine Learning

Operating systems Linux Ubuntu, Windows, MacOS

> Laboratory Cell culture, RNA extraction, DNA cloning, qPCR, animal tissue extraction, single-cell calcium imaging, FACS

Languages Portuguese (Native speaker), English (Fluent), German (Conversational), French

Education

University of Leicester Leicester, United Kingdom

PhD in Cell Physiology and Pharmacology

2006 - 2009

· Thesis title: Cloning and characterization of novel NMDA receptors splice variants in Glia

University of Aveiro Aveiro, Portugal

MSc in Molecular Microbiology

2002 - 2005

- Thesis title: The role of N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor subunits in Aß induced toxicity
- Host institution: Center for Neuroscience and Cell Biology (CNC), Coimbra, Portugal

University of Aveiro Aveiro, Portugal

BSc in Biology 1997 - 2001

- Semester project 1: Phytochelatin synthesis in Pisum sativum L. induced by zinc.
- Semester project 2: Identification of proteins that interact with protein phosphatase type 1 gamma subunit using the yeast two-hybrid approach.

Work Experience _____

Dewpoint Therapeutics GmbH

Dresden, Germany January 2021 - Present

SENIOR SCIENTIST (DATA SCIENCE) · Custom analysis of genomic data.

• Differential gene expression analysis for multiple disease programs (RNA-seq data).

- · Development of a Shiny application.
- Design RNA-seq experiments with R&D teams and liase with external CROs for their execution.
- · Design and implementation of ETL pipelines.
- Development of an internal R package for the analysis of mass-spectrometry measurements.
- · Prototyping of machine learning models.
- Leading several projects to set-up Data Science infrastructure in AWS (NF-Tower, Shiny server)
- Design of data ontologies for storage sample metadata.
- Evaluation and recommendation of Data Science products and Services.
- Supervision of a Data Science intern.
- · Lead projects executed by external contractors.

Scientific Computing Facility (Scionics GmbH), MPI-CBG

Dresden, Germany

June 2019 - December 2020

BIOINFORMATICS DATA ANALYST

- · Custom analysis of genomic data.
- Integration of multi-omics data (Ribo-Seq and RNA-seq datasets).
- Pipeline development for mass-spectrometry data.
- Pipeline development for long read sequencing (PacBio) to detect genomic insertions.
- Differential gene expression analysis (RNA-seq data).
- Teaching of a data analysis and visualization course (R) highly rated by students.
- Implementation of conda environments in production to increase reproducibility of data analysis.

FEBRUARY 16, 2022

Institute of Molecular Biology

Mainz, Germany
Dec. 2014 - May 2019

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER / BIOINFORMATICIAN

- Developed and implemented pipelines for small RNA analysis (piRNA, miRNA).
- · Integrated and analyzed multiple -omics datasets (smRNA-seq, mRNA-seq, total RNA-seq, ATAC-seq).
- Developed scripts and tools for custom sequencing data analysis.
- Designed and advised on the design of figures and best visualization practices.
- Tested the suitability of new library preparation kits / methods for next-generation sequencing.
- Coordinated the installation of a Zebrafish Facility Management database. I ensured good communication between the IT support, the fish facility manager and the database developer.
- Internal group teaching of UNIX command-line usage and bash.

Biotechnology Center TUD (Biotec)

Dresden, Germany

Oct. 2013 - Nov. 2014

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER / BIOINFORMATICIAN

- · Built a pipeline for variant calling from exome sequencing data.
- · Troubleshooting of sequencing issues.
- · Advised users on NGS experimental design.
- Liaised with clinical staff and organized the collection and processing of clinical samples.
- Analysis of chromatin associated proteins (DamID-seq and ChIP-seq)
- Differential gene expression (RNA-seq data).
- · T-cell receptor profiling.

Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics (MPI-CBG)

Dresden, Germany Oct. 2009 - Aug. 2013

MARIE CURIE POSTDOCTORAL FELLOW

- · Created new stable cell lines with tagged RNA-binding proteins.
- Prepared RNA samples for splice-junction arrays, RNA-seq and ChIP-seq.
- · Analyzed the data of all experiments of my project.
- Collaborated with students and Postdoctoral researchers in conceiving and analyzing experiments.
- · Trained doctoral students.

Center for Neuroscience and Cell Biology

Coimbra, Portugal May 2005 - Jan. 2006

CELL CULTURE TECHNICIAN

- Maintained mammalian cell lines and plated them for experiments according the requests of users.
- · Ordering and budgeting of cell culture reagents
- · Preparation of cell culture media.
- Teaching aseptic cell culture techniques and best practices to students.

Open source contributions _

Package maintainer Bioconductor

GeneOverlap May. 2020 - Present

- Fixed bugs to keep the package as part of Biocondutor.
- User support.

Teaching and mentoring _

Dewpoint TherapeuticsDresden, Germany

MACHINE LEARNING INTERN

2021

- Supervised an undergraduate student developing machine learning models.
- Fully remote supervision.

IMB alumni Dresden, Germany

IMB MENTORING PROGRAM

2021 - present

Mentoring of a PhD student at one of my former places of employment.

Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics

Dresden, Germany

Data Analysis and Visualization with R

2020

- Taught data manipulation (dplyr) and visualization (ggplot2).
- Students ranked the course very good or excellent in a survey.

Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics

Dresden, Germany

ALTERNATIVE SPLICING

2011

- Pre-doc practical course.
- · Taught chromatin imunnoprecipitation and 3'RACE.
- Supervised the students as they carried out the experiments.

FEBRUARY 16, 2022

Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics

Dresden, Germany

Leicester, United Kingdom

Leicester, United Kingdom

2011

- CHROMATIN IP AND RNA LOCALIZATION
- · Pre-doc practical course.
- · Taught primer design and qPCR.
- supervised the students whilst they carried out the experiments.

University of Leicester

LABORATORY SUPERVISION AND MENTORING OF A MEDICAL BSC STUDENT

2006 - 2007

2006 - 2007

2003

Coimbra, Portugal

- · Taught molecular biology techniques.
- Designed experiments and supervised daily work.
- For his project the student received a BSc Honours Degree.

University of Leicester

KEY SKILLS IN SCIENTIFIC WRITING AND PRESENTATION (MB1002)

- Pre-doc practical course.
- Advising 1st year BSc students on scientific communication.
- · Marking essays/presentations.

University of Coimbra

BASIC RESEARCH SKILLS TO MEDICAL STUDENTS

- · Semester long research project.
- · Introduced Medical students to cell biology techniques.
- · Supervised benchwork.

Grants, Honors & Awards

INTERNATIONAL

2011 - 2013 Marie Curie Intra-European fellowship for career development, FP7, U.E.

2002 Training program in molecular neuroscience scholarship, Prodep III, U.E.

Desdren, Germany Coimbra Portugal

Advanced courses & workshops_

2018	CSAMA 2018: Statistical Data Analysis for Genome Scale Biology, practical course	Brixen, italy.
2016	Project management workshop, Two day workshop	Mainz, Germany.
2013	Programming for Evolutionary Biology, Two weeks, intensive Practical course	Leipzig, Germany.
2013	"Software Carpentry", practical course	Freising, Germany.
2012	Introduction to Biopython, practical course	Leuven, Belgium.
2012	Advanced RNA-Seg and ChiP-Seg Data Analysis, practical course	Hinxton, United
2012	nuvaniceu niva-sey anu chir-sey bata miatysis, practical course	Kingdom.
2012	Principles of Light Microscopy, practical course	Desdren Germany.
2012	Pieces & parts: a primer on brain dissection from discrete regions to micronuclei, practical course	Aveiro, Portugal.

FEBRUARY 16, 2022

Publications & presentations

Asterisk (*) denotes equal contribution of the first two authors.

PEER-REVIEWED PAPERS

The RNA binding protein human antigen R is a gatekeeper of liver homeostasis

Subramanian, P., S. Gargani, A. Palladini, M. Chatzimike, M. Grzybek, M. Peitzsch, A. D. Papanastasiou, I. Pyrina, V. Ntafis, B. Gercken, M. Lesche, A. Petzold, A. Sinha, M. Nati, V. R. Thangapandi, I. Kourtzelis, M. Andreadou, A. Witt, A. Dahl, R. Burkhardt, R. Haase, **A. M. d. J. Domingues**, I. Henry, N. Zamboni, P. Mirtschink, K.-J. Chung, J. Hampe, Ü. Coskun, D. L. Kontoyiannis, and T. Chavakis *Hepatology* ()

Exosomal miRNAs from Prostate Cancer Impair Osteoblast Function in Mice

Furesi, G., A. M. de Jesus Domingues, D. Alexopoulou, A. Dahl, M. Hackl, J. R. Schmidt, S. Kalkhof, T. Kurth, H. Taipaleenmäki, S. Conrad, C. Hofbauer, M. Rauner, and L. C. Hofbauer

International Journal of Molecular Sciences 23.3 p. 1285. 2022

Membrane-associated cytoplasmic granules carrying the Argonaute protein WAGO-3 enable paternal epigenetic inheritance in Caenorhabditis elegans

Schreier, J., S. Dietz, M. Boermel, V. Oorschot, A.-S. Seistrup, **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, A. W. Bronkhorst, D. A. H. Nguyen, S. Phillis, E. J. Gleason, S. W. L'Hernault, C. M. Phillips, F. Butter, and R. F. Ketting

Nature Cell Biology pp. 1–13. 2022

Intrinsically disordered protein PID-2 modulates Z granules and is required for heritable piRNA-induced silencing in the Caenorhabditis elegans embryo

Placentino, M., A. M. de Jesus Domingues, J. Schreier, S. Dietz, S. Hellmann, B. F. de Albuquerque, F. Butter, and R. F. Ketting *The EMBO Journal* 40.3 e105280. 2021

* Extensive nuclear gyration and pervasive non-genic transcription during primordial germ cell development in zebrafish Redl, S., **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, E. Caspani, S. Möckel, W. Salvenmoser, M. Mendez-Lago, and R. F. Ketting *Development* 148.2 dev193060. 2021

Bardet-Biedl syndrome proteins modulate the release of bioactive extracellular vesicles

Volz, A.-K., A. Frei, V. Kretschmer, A. M. de Jesus Domingues, R. F. Ketting, M. Ueffing, K. Boldt, E.-M. Krämer-Albers, and H. L. May-Simera *Nature Communications* 12.1 p. 5671. 2021

Condensation of Ded1p Promotes a Translational Switch from Housekeeping to Stress Protein Production

Iserman, C., C. D. Altamirano, C. Jegers, U. Friedrich, T. Zarin, A. W. Fritsch, M. Mittasch, **A. Domingues**, L. Hersemann, M. Jahnel, D. Richter, U.-P. Guenther, M. W. Hentze, A. M. Moses, A. A. Hyman, G. Kramer, M. Kreysing, T. M. Franzmann, and S. Alberti *Cell* 181.4 pp. 818–831. 2020

Innate Immune Training of Granulopoiesis Promotes Anti-tumor Activity

Kalafati, L., I. Kourtzelis, J. Schulte-Schrepping, X. Li, A. Hatzioannou, T. Grinenko, E. Hagag, A. Sinha, C. Has, S. Dietz, **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, M. Nati, S. Sormendi, A. Neuwirth, A. Chatzigeorgiou, A. Ziogas, M. Lesche, A. Dahl, I. Henry, P. Subramanian, B. Wielockx, P. Murray, P. Mirtschink, K.-J. Chung, J. L. Schultze, M. G. Netea, G. Hajishengallis, P. Verginis, I. Mitroulis, and T. Chavakis *Cell* 183.3 771–785.e12.2020

* Maternal and zygotic gene regulatory effects of endogenous RNAi pathways

Almeida, M. V., A. M. d. J. Domingues, and R. F. Ketting

PLOS Genetics 15.2 e1007784. 2019

* RppH can faithfully replace TAP to allow cloning of 5'-triphosphate carrying small RNAs Almeida, M. V., **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, H. Lukas, M. Mendez-Lago, and R. F. Ketting Methods X 2019

PETISCO is a novel protein complex required for 21U RNA biogenesis and embryonic viability

Rodrigues, R. J. C., A. M. d. J. Domingues, S. Hellmann, S. Dietz, B. F. M. d. Albuquerque, C. Renz, H. D. Ulrich, P. Sarkies, F. Butter, and R. F. Ketting

Genes & Development 33.13-14 pp. 857-870. 2019

Tdrd6a Regulates the Aggregation of Buc into Functional Subcellular Compartments that Drive Germ Cell Specification

Roovers, E. F., L. J. T. Kaaij, S. Redl, A. W. Bronkhorst, K. Wiebrands, **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, H.-Y. Huang, C.-T. Han, S. Riemer, R. Dosch, W. Salvenmoser, D. Grün, F. Butter, A. van Oudenaarden, and R. F. Ketting

Developmental Cell 46.3 285–301.e9. 2018

Characterization of genetic loss-of-function of Fus in zebrafish

Lebedeva, S., A. M. de Jesus Domingues, F. Butter, and R. F. Ketting

RNA Biology 14.1 pp. 29-35. 2017

Enhancers reside in a unique epigenetic environment during early zebrafish development

Kaaij, L. J. T., M. Mokry, M. Zhou, M. Musheev, G. Geeven, A. S. J. Melquiond, **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, W. de Laat, C. Niehrs, A. D. Smith, and R. F. Ketting

Genome Biology 17 p. 146. 2016

Abundant cytomegalovirus (CMV) reactive clonotypes in the CD8+ T cell receptor alpha repertoire following allogeneic transplantation Link, C. S., A. Eugster, F. Heidenreich, E. Rücker-Braun, M. Schmiedgen, U. Oelschlägel, D. Kühn, S. Dietz, Y. Fuchs, A. Dahl, **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, C. Klesse, M. Schmitz, G. Ehninger, M. Bornhäuser, J. Schetelig, and E. Bonifacio

Clinical & Experimental Immunology 184.3 pp. 389-402. 2016

SR proteins are NXF1 adaptors that link alternative RNA processing to mRNA export

Müller-McNicoll, M., V. Botti, A. M. de Jesus Domingues, H. Brandl, O. D. Schwich, M. C. Steiner, T. Curk, I. Poser, K. Zarnack, and K. M. Neugebauer

Genes & Development 30.5 pp. 553-566. 2016

Tox: a multifunctional transcription factor and novel regulator of mammalian corticogenesis

Artegiani, B., A. M. de Jesus Domingues, S. B. Alonso, E. Brandl, S. Massalini, A. Dahl, and F. Calegari

The EMBO Journal 34.7 pp. 896-910. 2015

Identification of four functional NR3B isoforms in developing white matter reveals unexpected diversity among glutamate receptors.

Domingues, A. M. d. J., K. M. Neugebauer, and R. Fern

Journal of neurochemistry 117.3 pp. 449-60. 2011

Toxicity of beta-amyloid in HEK293 cells expressing NR1/NR2A or NR1/NR2B N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor subunits.

Domingues, A., S. Almeida, E. F. da Cruz e Silva, C. R. Oliveira, and A. C. Rego

Neurochemistry international 50.6 pp. 872-80. 2007

FK506 prevents mitochondrial-dependent apoptotic cell death induced by 3-nitropropionic acid in rat primary cortical cultures.

Almeida, S., A. M. de Jesus Domingues, L. Rodrigues, C. R. Oliveira, and A. C. Rego

Neurobiology of disease 17.3 pp. 435-44. 2004

PREPRINTS & OTHERS

Extensive nuclear gyration and pervasive non-genic transcription during primordial germ cell development in zebrafish Redl, S., **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, S. Möckel, W. Salvenmoser, M. Mendez-Lago, and R. F. Ketting *bioRxiv* p. 2020.01.10.901306. 2020

Identification of Tox chromatin binding properties and downstream targets by DamID-Seq

Jesus Domingues, A. M. de, B. Artegiani, A. Dahl, and F. Calegari

Genomics Data 7 pp. 264-268. 2016

REVIEWS

* White matter synapses: form, function, and dysfunction.

Alix, J. J. P. and A. M. de Jesus Domingues

Neurology 76.4 pp. 397-404. 2011

Glia as transmitter sources and sensors in health and disease.

Domingues, A. M. d. J., M. Taylor, and R. Fern

Neurochemistry international 57.4 pp. 359-66. 2010

CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

Expression of NR1/NR2B N-methyl-D-aspartate receptors enhances heroin toxicity in HEK293 cells. **Domingues, A.,** T. Cunha Oliveira, M. L. N. Laço, T. R. A. Macedo, C. R. Oliveira, and A. C. Rego

Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences 1074 pp. 458-65. 2006

ORAL PRESENTATIONS

A family portrait: global effects of SR protein depletion on alternative splicing

Jesus Domingues, A. M. de, M. Müller-McNicoll, M.-L. Ankö, and K. M. Neugebauer

8th Special Interest Group meeting on Alternative Splicing, 2011, Viena, Austria

NMDA Receptor Subunit composition Influences AßToxicity

Domingues, A., E. F. da Cruz e Silva, C. R. Oliveira, and A. C. Rego

 $34 th\, \textit{Meeting of the Portuguese Pharmacology Society}, 2003, Coimbra, Portugal$

SELECTED POSTER PRESENTATIONS

* Activation of the genome in germ cells in relation to transposon silencing and the piRNA pathway **Jesus Domingues**, **A. M.** de, S. Redl, E. Caspani, H. Dill, and R. F. Ketting

Mobile Genetic Elements and Genome Plasticity, 2018, Santa Fé, NM, USA

Regulation of gene expression by SR proteins: a comprehensive study

Jesus Domingues, A. M. de, M. Müller-McNicoll, and K. M. Neugebauer

Special Interest Group meeting on Integrative RNA Biology (AS-SIG), 2013, Berlin, Germany

Characterization of novel NMDA receptor subtypes

Jesus Domingues, A. M. de, M. G. Salter, and R. Fern

Society for Neuroscience, 2008, Washington, USA

References_

Ian Henry, PhD Rene Ketting, PhD

Karla M. Neugebauer, PhD

Head of Scientific Computing, MPI-CBG, Dresden. dr.ian.henry@gmail.com Scientific Director, IMB, Mainz (JGU). +49 6131 39 21470 / r.ketting@imb-mainz.de

 $Professor\ of\ Molecular\ Biophysics\ and\ Biochemistry\ and\ of\ Cell\ Biology,\ Yale\ University.\ +1\,203\,785\,3322\,/$

karla.neugebauer@yale.edu